Inventory to the Nasser Sharify Papers, 1902-1993 (Bulk 1950-1989)
Hoover Institution Archives
Nasser Sharify Papers
1902-1993 (Bulk 1950-1989)
86043
Sharify, Nasser, 1925-
Number of Containers: 102 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (50 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The Nasser Sharify papers document his long career as a librarian, academic, advocate, and consultant. The papers relate in part to the formulation of plans for the creation of a national library for Iran, and to development of library and information science schools, especially in Iran and Morocco, as well as to the development of international library programs at schools in the United States. The collection consists of reports, working papers for reports, correspondence, financial and legal records, minutes, conference papers, printed matter, sound recordings, microfilm, and photographs.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1986, with increments added in September 1988, June 1989, February 1998, and 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1925 September 23 Born, Tehran, Iran
1949-1953 Deputy director of Library of Parliament, Iran
1953 Came to the United States
1954 M.S., Columbia University
1958 PhD, Library Science, Columbia University
1959 Author, Cataloging Persian Works, Including Rules for Transliteration Entry Description
1960 Director of graduate training program, UNESCO Mission, National Teacher's College, Tehran
1966 Member of U.S. AID Mission to Turkey, Iran, and Pakistan
1966-1968 Director of international librarianship and documentation, International Studies and World Affairs, State University of New York (SUNY), Oyster Bay
1968-1987 Dean and professor of the Graduate School of Library and Information Science, Pratt Institute, Brooklyn, New York
1974-1975 Chairman of the board of consultants to the National University of Iran
1975-1977 Chairman of the board of consultants to the Pahlavi National Library of Iran
1987 Distinguished professor and dean emeritus, Pratt Institute
1999 June 30 Resolution honoring Nasser Sharify adopted by the Council of the American Library Association
Source: Sharify, Nasser. Who's Who in American Education, 65th edition
Scope and Content of Collection
The Nasser Sharify papers document his long career as a librarian, academic, advocate, and consultant. The papers relate in part to the formulation of plans for the creation of a national library for Iran, and to development of library and information science schools, especially in Iran and Morocco, as well as to the development of international library programs at schools in the United States. The collection consists of reports, working papers for reports, correspondence, financial and legal records, minutes, conference papers, printed matter, sound recordings, microfilm, and photographs.
The largest series of the collection contains records relating to the planning and construction of the Pahlavi National Library in Iran from 1975 to 1977. As chairman of the board of consultants on the project, Sharify brought together librarians and information professionals from around the world to create a plan for the operation of the library, as decreed by Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi and overseen by the deputy minister of the imperial court of Iran for cultural affairs, Shojaeddin Shafa. The resulting nine volume report is included in the collection along with supporting documents, draft reports, consultant correspondence, contracts, minutes, and recordings of planning conferences.
As evidenced by this project, Sharify spent much of his career promoting international librarianship as a profession. The collection includes essays, reports, research materials, and correspondence relating to library education, cataloging practices, and book distribution in the United States, Iran, and Morocco from the 1950s to 1970s. In addition, Sharify's work with the Pratt Institute Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences, CENTO, and Unesco resulted in documents relating to international librarianship.
The International Library Manpower materials in the Conference, Institutes, and Workshops materials series include data collected from over fifty countries around the world, summarizing social, economic, and political conditions in relation to library education and resources.
Other materials of note include research materials related to Sharify's work on developing a transliteration and cataloging standard for Persian library materials. His work on this project, in the Research Projects series, included surveying libraries in the U.S. with Persian materials in their holdings.
A well-known figure in the library community, Sharify was highly active in a number of library associations, including the American Library Association (ALA), International Federation of Library Associations (IFLA), and the Association for Library and Information School Education (ALISE). Materials collected from conferences and meetings of these associations are included in the Professional Associations' Meetings and Offices Held in Professional Associations files. Among these materials are Sharify's speeches and writings from the conferences.
Arrangement
The arrangement of the collection follows a classification scheme developed by a former student of Nasser Sharify, for the purpose of donating the papers to the archives. In this classification scheme, each activity or project in Sharify's career is identified by a letter. For example, the creation of the Pahlavi National Library of Iran is identified by the letter "A"; materials from Offices Held in Professional Associations by the letter "K" and so on. Groups of documents related to each activity receive a numerical designation. There is no significance to the order which the groups are arranged or numbered. For example, materials in series "A" Pahlavi National Library have the following numbers as subseries or file:
A. Pahlavi National Library
A-1. Press, National and International
A-1/1. Comments by other professionals
A-2. Articles, brochures, and other printed matter about the PNL
Incremental materials are described using the same classification and series titles are repeated wherever related documents appear.
Access Points
Libraries--Iran.; Education.; Iran.; Kitabkhanah-i Pahlavi.; Library education--United States.; Library education--Iran.; Library education--Morocco.; Morocco.; Africa.; Unesco.
Inventory
- Pahlavi National Library file, 1975-1976 (Folder 1)
  Same as series "A- Pahlavi National Library file" but received in earlier shipment without designated classification. Maintained in original order
  - Position papers by the Board of Consultants and Nasser Sharify, vols. 1-5, 1976 (Folder 1)
  - Position papers by the Board of Consultants and Nasser Sharify, vols. 6-9, 1976 (Folder 2)
  - Position papers by the Board of Consultants and Nasser Sharify, vols. 10-11, 1976 (Folder 3)
  - Briefing documents, vols. 1-2, 1975 (Folder 3)
  - Final report, vols. 1-4, 1976 (Folder 4)
    Hard copy
  - Final report, vols. 5-6, 1976 (Folder 5)
  - Final report, vols. 1-2, 1976 (Folder 5)
    Soft copy
  - Final report, vols. 3-6, 1976 (Folder 6)
  - Consultants file, 1975-1976 (Folder 7)
    Includes correspondence, contracts, and biographical materials
    - Staff correspondence, 1975-1976 (Folder 7: 1-2)
    - Resumes of librarians, consultants, and secretaries, 1975-1976 (Folder 7: 3-6)
    - Biographical data, 1974-1975 (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, contracts, and biographical materials, 1974-1975 (Folder 7: 7)
      - A-C, 1975-1976 (Folder 7: 8-23)
      - C-L, 1975-1976 (Folder 8: 1-33)
      - L-S, 1975-1976 (Folder 9: 1-34)
      - S-Z, 1975-1976 (Folder 10: 1-32)
  - Microfilm of Pahlavi National Library reports and financial records (from Boxes 1-11) (Folder 11)
  - Financial records, 1975 (Folder 11-15)
    Includes paid invoices
  - Final report, vols. I-III, 1976 (Folder 15)
  - Final report, vols. IV-VI, 1976 (Folder 16)
  - Pamphlet summarizing PNL planning and objectives, 1976 (Folder 16)
  - Microfilm of financial records, correspondence, consultant contracts, final reports, and brochures (Folder 16)
    9 reels
    Copies of records in previous boxes
  - Articles and brochures about PNL (Folder 16)
  - Iranian and international press comments about PNL, 1975; 2 albums (Folder 17)
  - Comments by other professionals, 1975-1976; 1 album (Folder 17)
- A- Pahlavi National Library (PNL) file, 1975-1978 (Box 18-33, 83-96, 103)
  Includes correspondence, contracts, financial records, reports, minutes, charts, notes, photographs, sound recordings and microfilm
  - A-1. Press, national and international, 1975-1976 (Folder 18)
    Photocopies of album contents (Box 17)
  - A-3/1. The Pahlavi National Library of the Future: Its Resources, Services, Programs and Building Requirements, draft report, vols. 1-4, 1975 (Folder 18)
  - A-3/1 (Contd.). The Pahlavi National Library of the Future: Its Resources, Services, Programs and Building Requirements, draft report, vols. 5-9, 1975 (Folder 19)
  - A-3/1 (Contd.). The Pahlavi National Library of the Future: Its Resources, Services, Programs and Building Requirements, draft report, volumes 10-11, 1975 (Folder 20)
  - A-5. Conference and meeting materials, 1975 (Folder 20)
    - "Pahlavi National Library Records of Conferences and Meetings in Iran, Tape I," film reel, 1975 (Folder 20)
    - "Pahlavi National Library Records of Conferences and Meetings in Iran, Tape II," film reel, 1975 (Folder 21)
    - Compact cassette tapes of conferences in Iran regarding the Pahlavi National Library, 1975 (Folder 21)
      More description about recordings available in Box 21
    - Open reel tapes of conferences in Iran regarding the Pahlavi National Library, 1975 (Folder 22-23)
      13 7-inch reels
  - A-6. Consultants' biographical data, 1975-1976 (Folder 24: 1-7)
  - A-8. Consultants' biographical data, 1975-1976 (Folder 24: 8)
  - A-9. Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Folder 24: 9-15)
    Includes correspondence of Shojaeddin Shafa
  - A-9. Correspondence, 1976 (Folder 25-31)
    - Individuals (Folder 25-29)
      - General (Folder 25: 1)
      - A-D (Folder 25: 2-31)
      - E-K (Folder 26: 1-35)
      - L-R (Folder 27: 1-31)
      - S-V (Folder 28: 1-36)
      - W-Y (Folder 29: 1-17)
    - Institutions (Folder 29)
      - American Friends of the Middle East, 1975-1976 (Folder 29: 18)
      - American Library Association, 1976 (Folder 29: 19)
      - Asia Society, 1976 (Folder 29: 20)
      - Aspen Institute, 1976 (Folder 29: 21)
      - British Library, 1976 (Folder 29: 22)
      - Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1976 (Folder 29: 23)
      - Government Advisory Committee, 1976 (Folder 29: 24)
      - Iranian Consulate, 1975 (Folder 29: 25)
      - Middle East Institute, 1975-1976 (Folder 29: 26)
      - Ministry of Science and Higher Education (Iran), 1975-1976 (Folder 29: 27)
      - National Science Foundation, 1975-1976 (Folder 29: 28)
      - National Science Foundation, 1975-1976 (Folder 29: 29)
      - Plan and Budget Organization-Tehran, probably 1975 (Folder 29: 30)
      - Tehran Book Processing Center (TEBROC), 1975 (Folder 29: 31)
      - UNESCO, 1975 (Folder 29: 32)
      - UNISIST, 1976 (Folder 29: 33)
      - Miscellaneous, A-G, 1975-1976 (Folder 29: 34)
      - Miscellaneous, H-Z, 1975-1976 (Folder 30: 1-4)
    - Advisers, 1976 (Folder 30: 5)
    - Consultants, 1975-1979 (Folder 30: 6-11)
    - Copyright material, 1976 (Folder 30: 12)
    - Future publications, 1976 (Folder 30: 13)
    - Paperwriters acknowledgements, 1976 (Folder 30: 14)
    - Press releases, 1976 (Folder 30: 15)
    - Publicity, 1976 (Folder 30: 16)
    - Report to Dr. Sharify, 1975 (Folder 30: 17)
    - Sample letters, 1976 (Folder 30: 18)
    - Subject file. National Commission on Library and Information Science, 1975 (Folder 30: 19)
    - Telexes sent and received, 1975 (Folder 30: 20-22)
    - Thank you letters, 1975-1976 (Folder 30: 23)
  - A-9/1. Correspondence to consultants, 1975-1977 (Folder 31)
  - A-10. Organizational chart, 1976 (Folder 31)
    Includes slide
  - A-10. Photographs of consultants, circa 1976 (Folder 31)
  - A-10. Telephone directory of consultants, circa 1976 (Folder 31)
  - A-11. Implementation plan, 1975-1976 (Folder 32)
    - Administration and management, 1976 (Folder 32: 1)
    - Book and publications, 1976 (Folder 32: 2)
    - Design and construction, 1976 (Folder 32: 3)
    - Equipment and furniture, 1976 (Folder 32: 4)
    - Human resources, 1976 (Folder 32: 5)
    - Information systems, 1976 (Folder 32: 6)
  - A-12. Progress and administrative reports, 1975-1976 (Folder 32)
    - August 1975 Mission in Iran (Folder 32)
      - Administrative reports, 1975 (Folder 32: 7)
      - Register of tapes, 1975 (Folder 32: 8)
      - Supplemental reports, 1975 (Folder 32: 9)
    - Official documents list, 1975 (Folder 32: 10)
  - A-13. Copyright research file, 1976 (Folder 32: 11)
  - A-14. Fact sheets and miscellaneous reports, 1975-1976 (Folder 32: 12-15)
  - A-14. Miscellaneous reports on faculty and organizational structure, 1975-1976 (Folder 33: 1-2)
  - A-15. Architectural program and competition materials, 1975-1976 (Folder 33: 3-5)
  - A-16. Correspondence regarding publication of the final report, 1976 (Folder 33: 6)
- B- National University of Iran file, 1973-1974 (Box 34-36)
  Includes of reports, correspondence, contracts, financial records, and curriculum materials
  - B-1. Draft report, "Curriculum Study for National University of Iran, Tehran," preliminary draft, 1974 (Folder 34: 1)
  - B-2. Curriculum materials, 1973-1974 (Folder 34: 2-5)
  - B-2. Curriculum materials, 1973-1974 (Folder 35: 1-4)
  - B-3. Curriculum materials by subject, 1973-1974 (Folder 35: 5-11)
  - B-4. Final report, "Curriculum study of the National University of Iran,", 1974 October (Folder 36: 1)
  - B-5. Notes and reports from briefing and debriefing conferences for consultants, Tehran and Long Island, 1974 (Folder 36: 2-5)
  - B-6. Contracts, probably 1974 (Folder 36: 6)
  - B-7. Financial records and budget documents, 1974 (Folder 36: 7-9)
  - B-8. Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Folder 36: 10-13)
- C- National Teachers College (Daneshsarayeh-Ali) file, 1973-1974 (Box 36-37)
  For all material related to curriculum, financial records, contracts, briefing and debriefing, correspondence see:
  B-2 through B-8
  Includes comprehensive plan document
  - C-1. Comprehensive plan, volume 2, 1974 (Folder 36: 14)
  - C-1. Comprehensive plan, volume 3, 1974 (Folder 37: 1)
- D- Reza Shah Kabir University file, 1975 (Box 37)
  Includes reports and correspondence
  - D-1. "Academic Planning Report Prepared for the Trustees of Reza Shah Kabir University," Harvard University, 1975 (Folder 37: 2-4)
  - D-2. Planning report proposal for library instruction and research, 1976 (Folder 37: 5)
  - D-3. Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Folder 37: 6)
- E- Farah Pahlavi University file, 1976-1977 (Box 37)
  Includes correspondence, blueprint, and planning materials relating to Graduate School of Library and Information Science
  - E-1. Plans and correspondence, 1976-1977 (Folder 37: 8)
  - E-2. Blueprint of the building plan, 1976 (Folder 37: 9)
- F- Centre National de Documentation (C.N.D.) file, 1973-1981 (Box 38)
  Includes reports, correspondence, and planning materials
  - F-1. Reports of evaluation seminar, 1981 (Folder 38: 1)
  - F-2. Correspondence, 1981 (Folder 38: 2)
  - F-3. Plan de Développement Economique et Social, 1973-1977, vols. I-III (Folder 38: 3-5)
  - F-4. Plan de Développement Economique et Social, 1978-1982,, vols. 1-2 (Folder 38: 6)
- G- Meknes University file, 1980 (Box 38: 7)
  Includes proposal for creation of school
- H- Ecole des Sciences de l'Information, Morocco file, 1973-1983 (Box 38-42)
  Includes reports, curriculum materials, correspondence, bulletins, and planning materials
  - H-1. Mission reports to UNESCO and to the government of Morocco, 1974-1981 (Folder 39: 1-4)
  - H-2. Curriculum materials, 1981 (Folder 39: 5-8)
  - H-3. Ecole des Sciences d'Information theses, 1980 (Folder 40)
  - H-4. Planning documents and research materials, 1979-1980 (Folder 41: 1-5)
  - H-5. Syllabus, 1979 (Folder 41: 6-7)
  - H-6. Correspondence and financial documents, 1981 (Folder 42: 1-2)
  - H-7. Ecole des Sciences d'Information bulletins, 1983 (Folder 42: 3)
- I- Morocco projects file, 1970-1981 (Folder 42: 4)
  Includes ESI/CND related studies
- J- Professional associations' meetings file, 1954-1988 (Box 42-46, 103)
  Includes brochures, writings, speeches, correspondence, programs, and reports
  - J-1. International Federation of Library Associations (IFLA), 1964-1985 (Folder 42-43)
    - 1964, 1969 (Folder 42: 5)
    - 1972-1973 (Folder 42: 6)
    - 1974 (Folder 42: 7-8)
    - 1974-1975 (Folder 43: 1)
    - 1976 (Folder 43: 2-3)
    - 1977-1978 (Folder 43: 4)
    - 1979-1980 (Folder 43: 5)
    - 1980-1981 (Folder 43: 6)
    - 1981-1983 (Folder 43: 7)
    - 1984-1985 (Folder 43: 8-9)
  - J-2. International Federation for Documentations (FID), 1973 (Folder 43: 10)
  - J-3. American Library Association (ALA), 1966-1984 (Folder 44-45)
    - 1966 (Folder 44: 1)
    - 1967-1968 (Folder 44: 2-7)
    - 1968-1970 (Folder 44: 8-11)
    - 1971 (Folder 44: 12-13)
    - 1971-1973 (Folder 45: 1-5)
    - 1975 (Folder 45: 6-7)
    - 1976-1978 (Folder 45: 8)
    - 1983-1984 (Folder 45: 9-11)
    - 1984-1986 (Folder 46: 1-2)
  - J-4. Association of American Library Schools (AALS)/Association for Library and Information Science Education (ALISE), 1971-1972 (Folder 46: 3-6)
  - J-5. Special Library Association (SLA), 1971 (Folder 46: 7)
  - J-7. Other associations, 1973-1980 (Folder 46: 8)
- K- Offices held in professional associations file, 1964-1988 (Box 46-49, 103)
  Includes minutes, programs, speeches, writings, and conference materials
  - K-1. ALA - International Relation Round Table (IRRT) nominating committee correspondence and newsletters, 1960-1971 (Folder 46: 9-11)
  - K-2. ALA - UNESCO panel, 1966-1970 (Folder 46: 12)
  - K-3. ALA - Nominating committee, 1970-1972 (Folder 46: 13-14)
  - K-4. ALA - Library Education Division (LED) (Folder 47-48)
    - General, 1967-1974 (Folder 47: 1)
    - Board of Directors meetings, 1968-1972 (Folder 47: 2)
    - Committee on Equivalency and Reciprocity, 1962-1975 (Folder 47-48)
      - Budget, 1967-1971 (Folder 47: 3)
      - Correspondence, 1964-1971 (Folder 47: 4)
      - Committee on International Library Schools, 1968-1971 (Folder 47: 5)
      - Country resource panel files, 1968-1975 (Folder 47: 6-15)
      - Country resource panel files, 1968-1975 (Folder 48: 1-17)
      - Equivalency and reciprocity committee reports, 1968-1975 (Folder 48: 18-19)
      - Meeting, 1968-1969 (Folder 49: 1)
      - Reports and conference proceedings, 1962-1971 (Folder 49: 2-11)
      - Studies, related, 1968 (Folder 49: 12)
  - K-4/4. ALA/LED - Teacher's section, 1971-1974 (Folder 49: 13)
  - K-5. Public Library Association (PLA), 1982-1984 (Folder 49: 14)
  - K-5/1. PLA, International Relation Task Force, 1982-1983 (Folder 49: 15)
  - K-6. International Federation of Library Association (IFLA) Standing Advisory Committee, 1974-1976 (Folder 49: 16)
  - K-7. Council of National Library Association (CNLA) - Committee for visiting foreign libraries, 1964-1966 (Folder 49: 17)
  - K-8. Association for Library and Information Science Education - Governmental Relation Committee, 1984 (Folder 49: 18)
- L- State University of New York (SUNY), Department of International Studies and World Affairs file, 1966-1968 (Box 49-57)
  Includes reports, conference materials, correspondence, and writings
  - L-1. General papers, reports, and other administrative documents, 1984 (Folder 49: 19)
  - L-1. General papers, reports, and other administrative documents, 1966-1971 (Folder 50-51:)
  - L-2. International Librarianship, Learning Resources and Information Sciences (ILLRIS) reports, projects, and related administrative documents, 1966-1967 (Folder 52-54:)
  - L-3. ILLRIS correspondence, 1966-1968 (Folder 54-56:)
    Includes incoming and outgoing, interoffice, and general correspondence related to conferences, international studies programs, and general affairs of the department
  - L-4. ILLRIS Mexico on Microfilm program, correspondence, reports, and conference materials, 1967-1968 (Folder 56-57:)
- M- Pratt Institute Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences (GSLIS) file, 1968-1987 (Box 57-66)
  Includes correspondence, bulletins, reports, pamphlets, poster, and administrative documents
  - M-1. Dean's correspondence, 1960-1978 (Folder 57-61:)
    Includes correspondence while at SUNY (1966-1968) and the University of Pittsburgh (1963-1966); personal correspondence; routine correspondence from the Office of Dean and Assistant Dean regarding conferences and colloquia; and correspondence with individuals and groups, especially the American Library Association, mainly pertaining to international librarianship and the international librarianship program at Pratt
  - M-2. Reports, meeting minutes, and other administrative documents, 1984-1987 (Folder 61-65:)
  - M-3. Published bulletins, pamphlets, and brochures, 1965-1983 (Folder 65-66:)
- N- UNESCO Department of Libraries, Documentation and Archives and Department of Education file, 1958-1963 (Folder 66-67:)
  Includes reports, memoranda, and working documents
  - Reading Materials Project (Iran), 1962-1963 (Folder 66: 1-2)
  - UNESCO reports regarding library and information services around the world, 1962-1978 (Folder 66: 3-5)
  - Memoranda, 1962-1963 (Folder 66: 6)
  - Published reports, 1970-1980 (Folder 66: 7)
  - Published reports, circa 1980 (Folder 67: 1)
  - Intergovernmental Conference on the Planning of National Documentation, Library and Archives Infrastructures, reports and working documents, 1974 (Folder 67: 2)
  - Reports from seminars, 1963 (Folder 67: 3)
- O- University of Pittsburgh file, 1963-1966 (Box 67-68, 103)
  Includes pamphlets, brochures, clippings, and correspondence
  - O-1. Graduate School of Library and Information Sciences (GSLIS) materials, 1963-1966 (Folder 67: 4-6)
  - O-2. International Library Information Center (ILIC) statement of activities and related materials, 1964-1967 (Folder 68: 1-3)
  - O-3. Bibliothèque Français de Pittsburgh materials, 1966-1967 (Folder 68: 4)
- P- Research projects file, 1955-1988 (Box 68-73)
  Includes background materials, analysis, and preliminary reports
  - P-1. Research materials for articles on Iran in ALA World Encyclopedia, 1976-1984 (Folder 68: 5-6)
  - P-2. Research materials for article on libraries in Afghanistan in Encyclopedia of Library and Information Science, 1965 (Folder 68: 7)
  - P-2. Research materials for article on libraries in Afghanistan in Encyclopedia of Library and Information Science, 1965 (Contd.) (Folder 69: 1)